Mukesh Manral

Data Scientist - CloudyML

Profile

Tackling challenges in Data Science and Computer Vision, eager to leverage a diverse range of talents in a new and engaging professional setting. Committed to lifelong learnin and bring some positive change for business. 1+ year of proven experience architecting applications using Deep Learning, Machine Learning, Python with libraries such as tensorflow, keras, sklearn, numpy, panda, matplotlib, seaborn, Tableau for Data Visualization and Dashboarding. Recognized by Founder, CEO, and peers as a personable, dedicated performer who demonstrates Curiosity, Intellectual agility, Statistical fluency, Research stamina, Scientific rigor and Skeptical nature to ensure quality and timely project completion.

Technical Skills

Python • Machine Learning • Deep Learning • Computer Vision • AWS •
AWS Sagemaker • Streamlit • Pandas • Numpy • scikit-learn • tensor-flow • keras • opency

Professional Experience

Data Scientist, CloudyML ∂

June 2021 – present

Project-1: Customer Life Time Value Prediction

Responsibilities \ Achievements:

- Extracted and Preprocessed more than 30 Thousand Records, selected required Features as per the problem statement, data was divided in 8 different files by organization.
- Segregate most important customers based on RFM matrix as to Increase future sales as by decreasing churning customers number
- Used time saver Lifetimes Package

Other Responsibilities:

Responsibilitie-1:

- Developing Applied Python Projects for learners.
- Preparing crisp videos on Basic and Advance Python topics

Responsibilities-2:

- Upgrading AI For ALL Data Science Course, it includes:
- Maths Section : Aim is Applied Maths: Statics, Probability and Calculus-EDA
- Coding Section : Trying to Increase Implementation part as by producing more realtime simulated applied projects for Basic and Intermediate Python
- Machine Learning and Related Projects: Creating Machine Learning frameworks for every algorithm and related project, which are easy to understand and implement

Machine Learning Engineer, TechSim+

January 2020 – December 2020

Client: One Financial Corporation

One Financial Corporation is a bank holding company specializing in credit cards, auto loans, banking and savings accounts.

Project-1: Loan Underwriting

This project refers crucial process of a lender determining if a borrower's loan application is an acceptable risk. Based on the analysis of credit, capacity and collateral of customer, we manages to predict whether a particular customer could be sanctioned a Loan or not, in parallel predicted amount which could be sanctioned.

Responsibilities / Achievements:

- Preprocessed data of more than 77 Thousand Records and 30 Features.
- Built and Trained Machine Learning Models using different algorithms like Logistics Regression, Random Forest Classifier, Xgboost Classifier and Voting Classifier.
- Predicted Loan Amount which could be sanctioned to eligible customers using Linear Regression, Ridge Regression and Lasso Regression.
- Used matrices like Classification Reports, Confusion Matrix, AUC Score to find model accuracy.
- Ploted prediction graph using Matplotlib and Seaborn Librarys to show Loan Amount Predictions.

Project-2: Customer Churn Prediction

This project refers to the prediction of whether a particular customer ceases there relationship with a company.

Responsibilities / Achievements:

- Preprocessed data of more than 77 Thousand Records and 30 Features
- Built and Trained Machine Learning Models using different algorithms like Logistics Regression, Random Forest Classifier, Xgboost Classifier and Voting Classifier.
- Used matrices like Classification Reports, Confusion Matrix, AUC Score to find model accuracy.

Certification

Master Data Science for Industry-(Ascend Pro), Link: \mathscr{D}

November 2020 -October 2021

Attended 12 Months Training on Full Stack Data Science for Industry
Institute: Analytics Vidhya

Got exposure to following areas of Data Science:

- Tools like Python, Pandas, Numpy, Matplotlib, Seaborn, Scikitlearn, Keras, Tableau, MongoDB, SQL, Spacy, Spark, AWS.
- Industry like Cusumer Market and Telecom, Financial Services, Life Science and Farma.

Machine Learning by Stanford University (Coursera), Link: ⊘

May 2020 - July 2020

Achievements

Machine Hack Data Hackon, Link: ∂

Global Ranking of 315

Kaggle, Link: ∂

Pain Point: Like others I have to invested a ton of time and money in exploring Machine Learning and Deep Learning

AIM: To make easy to follow Machine Learning and Deep Learning framework in simple words Written easy to follow kernels on different Machine Learning Algorithms and Deep Learning

Github, Link: ∂

Sharing my knowledge with Data Science community

Education

Bachelor's in Computer Science Engineering, Uttarakhand Technical University June 2015 - July 2019